Finding aid to the Ronnie Gilbert papers SSC.MS.00536
Sophia Smith Collection
Ronnie Gilbert papers
1951-2010
Sophia Smith Collection
Gilbert, Ronnie
SSC.MS.00536
14.5 linear feet (7 record cartons, 1 flat oversize box, plus 9 boxes. Other materials in the collection: Flat file)
The collection contains the personal and professional papers of Ronnie Gilbert, singer, playwrite, psychotherapist, narrator of numerous documentary films, feminist, and global peace worker. Also includes extensive audiovisual materials documenting concerts, albums, and interviews with Ronnie Gilbert and others.
Conditions Governing Access
Open with caveat: collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Financial records from Acc.#11S-14 are separated and restricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Ronnie Gilbert in 2006, by Lisa Weg in 2011, and by Donna Korones in 2018.
Biographical Note
The singer, playwrite, psychotherapist, narrator of numerous documentary films, feminist, and global peace worker Ronnie Gilbert was born on September 7, 1926, in Brooklyn, New York, the daughter of Sarah Bekerman, a dressmaker, and Charles Gilbert, a factory worker and (later) owner in the needle trades. She had one sister, born in 1928. Gilbert worked in a U.S. government office as a clerk-typist during World War II. She began singing on radio shows at age twelve, and was a founding member of the folk group, The Weavers (1947). Gilbert was blacklisted during the McCarthy Era, along with the rest of the Weavers, due to her political beliefs, putting her performing career in temporary abeyance. She earned a M.S. degree in clinical psychology from Lone Mountain College in 1974, and practiced psychotherapy for eight years afterwards. Gilbert's career in the performing arts spanned over fifty years and included acting, singing, recording, teaching, and play-writing. In addition to her work with The Weavers, she recorded albums and performed with Holly Near and Adrienne Torf and narrated numerous documentary films. Gilbert was active in feminist and global peace work, and frequently lectured and gave workshops. She took a strong role in the work of the Women In Black organization, challenging U.S. policy in the Middle East and around the world.
Gilbert was married to Martin Weg in 1950, and had one daughter, Lisa Weg (born 1952). The couple divorced in 1959. Gilbert met Donna Korones during a 1984 tour with HARP (an acronym for Holly, Arlo, Ronnie, and Pete), and came out as a lesbian after the two started dating. They were legally married in 2004 in San Francisco, and lived together in California for much of their relationship. Ronnie Gilbert died on June 6, 2015, of natural causes.
Other Finding Aids
Some accessions have container lists that are available upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Related Materials
Voices of Feminism Oral History Project and the Dee Mosbacher papers and Woman Vision records.
Scope and Contents
The Ronnie Gilbert Papers consist of awards and citations for Gilbert's work as a singer and as a peace and social justice activist; drafts of numerous muscial scores; and publications and clippings concerning her career as a performer and her work as narrator for the film by Ken Burns, Not For Ourselves Alone. The collection contains correspondence, printed materials, research, writings, and memorabilia. Scripts and writings from the 1990s and 2000s include plays and a book manuscript about labor activist Mother Jones. Also included are some personal materials, as well as extensive audiovisual materials documenting concerts, albums, and interviews with Ronnie Gilbert and others.
Weavers (Musical group); Singers--United States--Biography--20th century--Sources; Working class women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; clippings; Diplomas; Awards; Sheet music; Posters; Financial records; Plays; Publications; Research; Scripts; Videotapes; DVD video discs; Audiocassettes; Floppy disks; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Gilbert, Ronnie; Weg, Lisa Charlene; Korones, Donna; Gilbert, Ronnie; Weg, Lisa Charlene; Korones, Donna
- Ronnie Gilbert papers and audiovisual materials, 2019-S-0002; Korones, Donna; 9.25 linear feet (7 record cartons, 1 flat oversize box); 4.25 linear feet (3 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box) audiovisual materials, including audiocassettes, videotapes, reel-to-reel recording studio tapes, DVDs, CDs, and floppy disks
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Donna Korones
  Scope and Contents
  Papers include concert scheduling and information, music orders, correspondence, press coverage, and personal materials; also includes extensive audiovisual materials documenting concerts, albums, and interviews with Ronnie Gilbert and others.
  Audiotapes; Videotapes; DVD video discs; Floppy disks; Korones, Donna
  - Personal papers related to marriage, anniversary, birthday, vacation, and hospice care, 1989-2015; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Memoir and memoir book proposal, 2005, 2015; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photo album made by Ronnie Gilbert on her 80th birthday, 2006 September 7; 1 items (1 CD); 1.29 Gigabytes (145 digital files) (Box 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This material was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  - AA Music orders, 1981-1990; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - News clippings, bio notes, articles, and performance reviews, 1983-1997; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Concert bookings, contracts, performance information, and setlists, 1968-1996; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
    - This Train Still Runs" with Ronnie Gilbert and Holly Near, 1996-1997; 1 folders (Box 1)
      - Near-Gilbert: FF mix disk for "This Train Still Runs", 1996; 1 items (1 floppy disk); .00540 Gigabytes 117 digital files (text files) (Box 1)
  - Video recordings, including TV broadcasts, concerts with Holly Near, the National Women's Music Festival, The Weavers, and Judy Small, dub VHS tapes, and personal tapes from Ronnie Gilbert's 70th birthday; also includes CD duplicates, 1983-2004; 2.5 linear feet 2 record cartons (65 VHS tapes, 1 slim videocassette); 17 items (17 CD duplicates) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Audio recording studio master tapes and reel-to-reel records of Ronnie Gilbert albums and singles, 1985-1989; 12 items (12 tapes) (Box 6, Box 8)
  - Audio recordings of interviews, radio broadcasts, concerts, Mother Jones, and individual tracks, 1984-1996; 1.25 linear feet 1 record carton (135 audiocassette and microcassette tapes) (Box 7)
- 2006 Accession, Accession 2006-S-0071
  - Books, pamphlets, correspondence, and notes about Mother Jones, feminism, and labor history (books annotated by Gilbert), 1974-2002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2006 (Box 1)